以下内容提供
the following content is provided under
CreativeCommons许可您的支持
a Creative Commons license your support
将帮助MITOpenCourseWare继续
will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
提供高质量的教育资源
offer high quality educational resources
免费
for free
捐款或查看额外的捐款
to make a donation or to view additional
数百个麻省理工学院课程的材料
materials from hundreds of MIT courses
访问位于ocw.mit.edu的麻省理工学院开放式课件
visit MIT opencourseware at ocw.mit.edu
好吧首先要做的事情
well ok so first important things about
课程计划然后
the course plans for the course and then
我今天要搬到新的地方了
I'm today I'm going to move to the new
下一节的注释部分2或
next section of the notes section 2 or
第2部分我应该说，实际上我会
part 2 I should say and actually I'll
暂时跳过第2节1并继续
skip for the moment section 2 1 and go
第2节2和所有SEC的全部
to section 2 2 and all the SEC's all of
第2章可能会来找你
chapter 2 will come to you probably
今天或最近明天这样就到了哪里
today or latest tomorrow so that's where
接下来我们要继续关注
we're going next we're following the
除了我要去之外，我都非常小心地注意到
notes pretty carefully except I'm going
跳过有关张量的部分，直到我
to skip the section on tensors until I
学到更多
learn more
基本上是啊是的我可以说一点点
basically yeah yeah I could say a little
关于张量，但这会流动这种流动
about tensors but this flows this flows
自然地使用SVD所以它只是
naturally using the SVD so it's just
非常重要的问题最小二乘
terribly important problem least squares
当然，我知道你见过
and of course I know that you've seen
一种或两种方法做最小的方格和
one or two ways to do least squares and
这真的是整个主题来了
it's really the whole subject comes
我在这里想说些什么
together here I want to say something
在我发出寻找计划之前
before I send out a plan for looking
整个课程都是如此
ahead for the course as a whole so
没有期末考试，我也没有
there's no final exam and I don't really
看看如何检验你如何进行测试
see how to examine you how to give tests
我当然可以创建我们的测试用途
I could of course create our tests use
关于线性代数部分，但是
it on about the linear algebra part but
我不认为这不是那种
I don't think it's it's not sort of the
本课程的风格
style of this course to
期待您快速创建证明
to expect you quickly to create a proof
或者在我们班上的东西，但我想
or something in in our class but I think
所以我想，特别是看
so I think and especially looking at
我们走向了什么，走得很远
what we're headed for and moving quite
所有这些都是朝这个方向稳步前进的
steadily in that direction is all these
这些线性的所有问题
all the problems that these this linear
代数是针对一个
algebra is is aimed at right up to an
包括共轭梯度下降和
including conjugate gradient descent and
并深入学习大
and deep learning the the big the
非常重要和活泼
overwhelmingly important and lively
活跃的研究领域，我不能
active research area that's I couldn't
做得比保持上课更好
do better than to get keep the course
走向那个方向所以我想是什么
going in that direction so I think what
我想请你做的是后期和下旬
I would ask you to do is late late and
排序四月/五月的常规家庭作业
sort of april/may the regular homeworks
我会在某个时刻停止并且
I'll discontinue at a certain point and
相反，我会问
then instead I'll be asking and
鼓励一个我不知道的项目
encouraging a project I don't know if
这是正确的字被使用
that's the right word to be using in
你使用我们所做的和
which you use what we've done for and
我会发出一个关于恒星的消息
I'll send out a message on stellar
列表只有五六个区域
listing like five or six areas and only
我的意思是其中一个是机器
I mean one of them is the machine
学习深度学习的部分，但他们是
learning deep learning part but they're
这一切的所有其他部分
all the other parts that that that
事情我们已经学会了正在学习如何
things we've learned to are learning how
如何找到稀疏的解决方案
to do how to find sparse solutions for
关于。的例子或者什么
example or or something about the
伪逆各种事情，所以
pseudo-inverse all kinds of things so
我的目标是给你
that's my goal is to would give you
使用这种材料的事情
something to do which uses the material
你已经学会了，我不是
you've learned and look I I'm not
期待论文，但这是一个
expecting a thesis but it's a it's a
好机会所以它不仅仅是
good chance so it will be more than just
喜欢拖一些代码进行深度学习
like drag in some code for deep learning
和一些数据矩阵并做到这一点
and and some data matrix and do it
但我们会粉笔amaura这是一个时间
but we'll chalk amaura that's a time
来
comes
就像我以前想的那样
so like I just thought I'd say before
发出我要说的公告
sending out the announcement I would say
它正在成为一个更大的东西
it's coming about what as a as a larger
规模超过单一一周的作业
scale than single one week homeworks
会在这里，他看到了
would be here before and he saw it's
关于我没有给它我没有
about that I haven't given it I haven't
给你的详细信息，以便让我做到这一点与
given you details so let me do that with
一条消息，然后再问，但我
a message and then ask again but I'm
我希望你能理解我的想法
open to I hope you've understood I think
你有，如果你做
you have that that if you make
直接建议我的电子邮件
suggestions either directly to my email
或在广场或任何他们得到报酬
or on Piazza or whatever they get paid
注意好的米歇尔，你就去
attention to okay Michelle you just go
与最小二乘转发有啥
forward with least squares so what's the
最小二乘问题，这些是什么
least squares problem and what are these
每个人带来的四种方式让我这样
four ways each each bringing so let me
首先谈谈伪逆
speak about the pseudo-inverse first
好的矩阵的伪逆
okay the pseudo inverse of a matrix
好吧，所以我们有一个Mby矩阵
alright good so we have a matrix a M by
N和伪逆我要去
N and the pseudo-inverse I'm going to
叫一个加号，它自然就会发生
call a plus and it naturally it's gonna
我将会乘以那些
be n by M I'm going to multiply those
在一起，我会得到尽可能接近
together and I'm gonna get as near to
尽我所能，这是我的想法
the identity as I can that's the idea of
当然是伪逆的这个词
course of the pseudo-inverse the word
伪就在那里，所以没有人
pseudo is in there so so no one's
欺骗了它不是一个真正的逆哦
deceived it's not an actual inverse oh
如果矩阵是正方形并且有一个
if the matrix is square and has an
当然反过来，如果反过来
inverse of course then if if a inverse
存在哪个需要每个人
exists which which requires a everybody
记得它需要矩阵
remembers it requires the matrix to be
square是因为我的意思是两者相反
square because I mean inverse on both
双方和它需要完整的排名
sides and and it requires rank in full
等级然后你可以存在逆
rank then the inverse will exist you can
检查它MATLAB会检查它
check it MATLAB would check it by
计算消除的枢纽
computing the pivots in elimination
找到并转动所以如果反过来
finding and pivots so if a inverse
存在意味着a和a次a
exists which means a and a times a
逆和反两次给出
inverse and a inverse times a both give
然后我加一个当然是逆
I then a plus is a inverse of course the
伪逆是那里的逆
pseudo inverse is the inverse when there
是一个，但我正在考虑案件
is one but I'm thinking about cases
其中或者所述矩阵是矩形的
where either the matrix is rectangular
或者它具有零特征值就是它
or or it has zero eigenvalues it it's it
可以是正方形但具有零空间
could be square but has a null space
除了其他的零矢量
other than just the zero vector in other
这些列依赖于什么可以
words the columns are dependent what can
然后我们做反转它我们做不到
we do then about inverting it we can't
如果a有空，则逐字地反转它
literally invert it if if a has a null
然后当我乘以向量X时的空间
space then when I multiply by a vector X
在那个零空间ax将是零和
in that null space ax will be zero and
当我乘以倒数仍然为零时
when I multiply by a inverse still zero
这不能改变零，所以如果有
that can't change the zero so if there
是null空间中的X然后是这个
is an X in the null space then this
不可能发生，但我们只是做到最好
can't happen but so we just do the best
我们可以，这就是伪
we can and that's what the pseudo
逆是，所以让我画一幅画
inverse is and so let me draw a picture
你知道的那张照片
of the the picture you know of the row
空间和零空间没关系，这是
space and the null space okay and it's
在那里你看到有一个零空间和
there you see there is a null space and
在这里我有列空间和
over here I have the column space and
转置的零空间还可以
the null space of a transpose okay so
这是行空间当然是一个
this is the row space of course that's a
一个和一个转置的列空间
column space of a and of a transpose and
有一个好这样的列空间
there's the column space of a okay so
该图片的哪一部分是可逆的
which part of that picture is invertible
以及图片的哪一部分
and which part of the picture is
绝望的顶部是可逆的
hopeless the top part is invertible this
是我们的维度行
is the are sort of our dimensional row
空间我们的维柱空间a
space our dimensional column space a
在这里采取矢量zaps它进入
takes a vector in here zaps it into
每一个哦，你总是在列中
every oh you always end up in the column
这里的空间在这里我带一个矢量
space here here here I take a vector in
该
the
行空间说X，它被映射到ax
row space say X and it gets mapped to ax
在这两个空间之间是一个
and between those two spaces a is
完全可逆，你知道你得到了
entirely invertible you know you you get
这里单独的向量分开
separate vectors here go to separate
列空间中的向量和
vectors in the column space and the
反向只是把它带回来所以我们知道
inverse just brings it back so we know
什么伪逆应该做的
what the pseudo-inverse should do
我们会采取这样的方式
it'll take a we'll take go that way and
加上伪逆将是正义的
a plus the pseudo-inverse will be just
它会给我们的上半
it will give us on the top half of the
图片它会给我们一个加号，我们会采取
picture it'll give us a plus we'll take
现在斧头回到上半部分的x4
ax back to x4 in the in the top half now
这就是我们所拥有的
what about here that's where we have
麻烦我们没有那些破坏
trouble we don't have that's what spoils
如果有一个零空格，我们的逆
our inverse if there's a null space
矢量然后它去你的地方
vector then it goes where when you
乘以null空间中的这个人
multiply by a this guy in the null space
通常沿着直线变为零
goes to zero usually along a straighter
行比我画，但去那里得到
line than I've drawn but go there gets
为零，所以你不能从提高它
to zero so you you can't raise it from
死者可以说你无法恢复
the dead so to speak you can't recover
你们其中一个人没有办法反过来
it one of you there's no way inverse so
我们必须考虑反向做什么
we have to think what shall a inverse do
在这里没有人的空间
to this space here where nobody's
击中它所以这就是这样
hitting it so it's this was this would
是转置的零空间，因为
be the null space of a transpose because
8/8对不起，应该是什么
8/8 sorry yeah what should the
伪逆我说的应该是什么
pseudo-inverse do I said what should the
反向做反过来是无奈的但是
inverse do the inverse is helpless but
我们必须要定义一个加号我说过
we have to to define a plus I've said
该怎么办呢
what it should do on that guy on the
列空间它应该采取一切
column space it should take everything
在它后面的列空间中
in the column space back where it came
从但它应在此做
from but what should it do on this
正交空间，耶，我告诉我
orthogonal space where yeah just tell me
如果我有什么，你会怎么想？
what what what do you think if I have
这里有一些矢量就是所谓的
some vector here that's it's called that
VR加一个会
V R plus one that would
就像这里在这里我有一个基础
be like so here here I have a basis of a
很好的列空间的良好基础
nice a nice basis for the column space
这个V我会用V代替
this V's I would use V's for the for the
那些出现在SVD中的人
ones that come up in the SVD they're
正交，它们来自正交
orthogonal and they come from orthogonal
使用，以便上半部分是伟大的
use so that top half is great what shall
我会用这些东西来做，我会发送的
I do with this stuff I'm gonna send that
加一个加号，我去哪里
back by a plus and where am I going what
我会把它发送给它知道
am I gonna do with it send it to know
在哪里它可以变为零是正确的
where else could it go zero is the right
回答所有这些东西都回归零
answer all this stuff goes back to zero
我正在寻找线性Mayton线性
I'm looking for a linear Mayton linear
算子矩阵，我不得不考虑
operator a matrix and I have to think of
一旦我决定如何处理所有人
once I've decided what to do with all
这些以及如何处理所有这些
those and what to do with all these then
我知道如何处理任何组合
I know what to do with any combination
所以我知道了我有这么所以
so I've got it I've got it so so the
这个想法对于X来说是真实的
idea will be this is true for X in the
如果是X，则行空间中X的行空间
row space for X in the row space if X is
在行空间中，ax位于列中
in the row space ax is in the column
空间和逆转只是把它带回来
space and a inverse just brings it back
因为它应该和在一个案例中
as it should and and in a in the case of
发生了可逆的矩阵
an invertible matrix a what happens to
我的照片是什么照片
my picture what does this picture
看起来如果a实际上是6乘
looking like if a is actually a six by
在这种情况下六个可逆矩阵
six invertible matrix in that case
什么是我的图片和什么是什么
what's what's in my picture and what is
所有这些零空间都不在我的照片中
not in my picture all this null space
东西不存在零空间
stuff isn't there a null space is just
零向量，但不论我做不
the zero vector but all that I don't
不得不担心，但总的来说我做
have to worry about but in general I do
不得不说，这样的一点是，
have to say so that the point is that a
加上我称之为什么
plus on the what what am i calling this
哦它是转置的空间或
ooh it's a null space of a transpose or
或者VR上的任何内容加上N到1
or whatever on on V R plus 1 to the N
那些虽然那些
those those though
那些人都是那些人
those all those vectors the the guys
那些不是正交的
that are not in the orthogonal to the
列空间然后你我们必须
column space then your your we have to
说什么加分对他们和他们做了什么
say what does a plus do to them and the
答案是它将所有这些都归零
answer is it takes them all to zero so
有一张照片使用我所说的
there's a picture using the what I call
线性代数的大图
the big picture of linear algebra the
你看到四个空格应该加分
four spaces you see what a plus should
现在我需要一个小公式
do now I need a little formula for it
我有一个我已经有了它的计划
I've got a I've got the plan for what it
应该是，而且它们有点像
should be and it's they're sort of a
自然的事情所以A加上你可以
natural thing so A plus a is you could
说它不是投影矩阵
say up it's a projection matrix it's not
单位矩阵因为因为如果是X.
the identity matrix because because if X
在零空间中加上ayayay
is in the null space a plus ay ay ay
加上a将把它归零，但是如此
plus a will take it to zero but so so
这是一个项目加一个是身份
it's a project a plus a is the identity
在上半部分，在底部为零
on the top half and zero on the bottom
那一半真的是那个
half that's that's really what the
矩阵是，现在我想要一个简单的
matrix is and now I want a simple
公式，而我想我的消息
formula for it and I guess my message
这里要说的是，如果我们正在寻找一个不错的
here is that if we're looking for a nice
表达式从SVD开始，因为
expression start with the SVD because
SVD适用于任何矩阵和它
the SVD works for any matrix and it
将其写为正交矩阵时间
writes it as an orthogonal matrix times
对角矩阵乘以正交
the diagonal matrix times an orthogonal
矩阵，现在我想反转它
matrix and now I want to invert it well
假设a的反转是什么
suppose a had an inverse what would that
如果这是F可逆的话
be if this is F invertible what would be
反向的SVD是什么的
the SVD of a inverse what would be the
奇异值分解，如果这样
singular value decomposition if if this
很好，所以这什么时候会好的
is good so when is this going to be good
什么会使我做什么
that what would that make what would I
必须知道那个矩阵西格玛
have to know about that matrix Sigma
中间的对角矩阵if
that diagonal matrix in the middle if
这确实是一个可逆矩阵以及
this is truly an invertible matrix well
知道那些不是它的名字
know what's its name those are not
特征值很好，我可以的价值
eigenvalues well there I can values of
a转置a但它们的奇异值
a transpose a but their singular value
奇异的紫罗兰很好，所以这就是
singular violets fine so that's the
奇异值矩阵和将会是什么
singular value matrix and what would be
如果a有反转的情况
the situation if if a had an inverse
所有人都没有零
there would be no zeros all their
奇异的价值观将坐在那里
singular values would be sitting there
Sigma12SigmaN会是什么样的
Sigma 1 2 Sigma N what would be the
这个Sigma矩阵的形状，如果我是
shape of this Sigma matrix if if if I
有一个逆，然后我必须它
have an inverse then I've it's got to be
广场和N所以它的形状是什么
square and by N so what's the shape of
西格玛的家伙也是正方形而且是如此
the Sigma guy also square and by n so so
可逆的情况将是，我
the invertible case would be and I'm
要消除这种在一分钟内
gonna erase this in a minute the
可转换的情况将是Sigma的时候
invertible case would be when Sigma is
只是那将是可逆的
just that that would be the invertible
如此让我们看看你能完成这个吗？
case so let's see can you finish this
公式什么是SVD
formula what would be the SVD of a
所以我给了我一个SVD
inverse so I've given the SVD of a I'm
鉴于U和这个西格玛很酷
given the U and this Sigma is cool and
V转置了与之相反的东西
the V transpose what's the inverse of
那
that
好吧，我真的在问你
well yeah I'm just really asking you
什么是该产品的反转
what's the inverse of that product of
这是第一个来自V的三个矩阵
three matrices what comes first here V
V转置的倒数是V的
the inverse of V transpose is V that's
因为V是正交矩阵
because V is a orthogonal matrix the
西格玛的倒数我只是1
inverse of Sigma I just 1 over it is
只是西格玛反转显然是什么
just the Sigma inverse it's obvious what
这意味着U的逆转
that means and the inverse of U would go
这里并为U转伟大确定，所以
here and that is U transpose great ok so
如果我们可逆，这是可逆的
this is f invertible if invertible we
知道逆转的SVD是什么
know what the SVD of a inverse is it
只需将V带回欧盟
just takes the V's back to the eu's
接受它或他们使用回到V的
takes it or they use back to the V's
无论哪个好，现在我们必须这样做
whichever ok ok now we've got to do it
如果我们要允许的话
if we're going to allow if we're gonna
超出这个限制的情况
get beyond this limit the situation
允许矩阵Sigma为矩形
allow the matrix Sigma to be rectangular
然后让我告诉你这个想法
then let me just show you how the idea
这里
here
所以现在我要说现在Sigma
so so now I'm gonna say now Sigma in
一般它的矩形它是我们的非
general its rectangular it's got our non
在对角线上零，但然后它退出
zeros on the diagonal but then it quits
所以它有一堆零
so it's it's got a bunch of zeros that
使它不可逆但是让我们做
to make it not invertible but let's do
我们最好和伪逆现在好了
our best and pseudo-inverse okay so now
我会帮助我开始一个公式
I'll help me get started on a formula
使用我想写这个加号
for using I want to write this a plus
就那里所描述而言
which are described up there in terms of
现在我要描述的子空间
the subspaces now I'm going to describe
关于Sigma和V的加分
a plus in terms of you Sigma and V the
在SVD的家伙还好，那应该是什么
in the SVD guys okay so what what shall
我从这里开始，让我给一个
I start with here well let me give a
暗示我只是这是一个很好的开始
hint I'll just that was a great start my
V仍然是正交矩阵V.
V is still an orthogonal matrix V
转置仍然是正交矩阵
transpose is still an orthogonal matrix
我会在最后反转它
I'll invert it at the end
U对所有问题都没有问题
the U was no problem all the problems
在Sigma和Sigma中都记得Sigma
are in Sigma and Sigma remember Sigma so
它是矩形的，也许我会成功
it's it's rectangular maybe I'll make it
喜欢广泛，也许我会
like wide for to wide and maybe I'll
只给它非零，然后全部
only give it to non zeros and then all
其余的，所以我的矩阵a的等级是2
the rest so the rank of my matrix a is 2
但是m和n大于2
but the m and n are bigger than 2 it's
它只有两个独立的列
it's just got two independent columns
然后它只是完全一点
and then then it's just sort of totally
单数好吧所以我的问题是什么
singular okay so my question is what am
我会把它放在那里，我已经描述过了
I going to put there and I've described
这是一种方式，但现在我要描述它
it one way but now I'm gonna describe it
另一种方式让我说出我的意思
another way well let me just say what I
我将放在那里的是伪
what I'll put there is the pseudo
西格玛的逆转我不能把西格玛
inverse of Sigma I can't put Sigma
反过来你使用那个符号，因为它
inverse you using that symbol because it
没有这样的事我不能
there is no such thing with this I can't
颠倒它，这是我能做到的最好的
invert it so that's the best I can do so
我差不多完成但是要完成我必须这样做
I'm almost done but to finish I have to
告诉你那是什么
tell you what does that
什么是这个东西，所以西格玛加
what what is this thing so Sigma plus
我现在要告诉你Sigmaplus和
I'm now going to tell you Sigma plus and
那就是应该坐在那里的东西
then that's what should sit there in the
如果西格玛是这个对角线那么中间
middle so if Sigma is this diagonal
在两个Sigma之后退出的矩阵
matrix which quits after two Sigma's
什么西格玛加上第一个好
what should Sigma plus be well first of
它应该是另一个矩形
all it should be rectangular the other
如果这是Mbyn列和
way if this was M by n column and
列和M行现在我想要n
columns and M rows now I want to have n
行和M列，是的，这是
rows and M columns and yeah here's the
质疑什么是最好的逆转你
question what's the best inverse you
能想出对于适马我的意思
could come up with for that Sigma I mean
如果有人独立于1806五，如果
if somebody independent of 1806 five if
有人要求你尽力反转
somebody asks you do your best to invert
那个矩阵我想我们都同意它
that matrix I think we'd all agree it is
是的，一个人会超过西格玛
yeah one over the Sigma one would come
那里有一个超过西格玛2然后非
there and one over Sigma two then non
零，然后零我认为你只是
zeros and then zeros I think you just
在那里，我们没有，我们没有
the way up there we didn't we didn't
知道该怎么做
know what to do
什么时候没有什么好做的零
when there was nothing good to do zero
是这样的答案是对的吗？
was there was the right answer so so
当然这都是零
this is all zeroes of course it's
另一种方式是矩形，但你看到了吗？
rectangular the other way but do you see
如果我乘以Sigma加倍
that if I multiply Sigma plus times
Sigma，如果我乘以伪逆
Sigma if I multiply the pseudo inverse
倍矩阵我会得到什么，如果我
times the matrix what do I get if I
乘以那就是那个
multiply that by that what does that
您可以描述乘法产品
multiplication produce can you describe
当你告诉我什么时，我还可以
the well or I can when you tell me what
看起来我会把它写下来所以
it looks like I'll write it down so what
如果Sigma是a，则是Sigma加上时间Sigma
is Sigma plus time Sigma if Sigma is a
对角线Sigmaplus是对角线和
diagonal Sigma plus is a diagonal and
两个人之后他们都退出了
they both quit after two guys what do I
有一个因为Sigma1倍1
have one because Sigma 1 times 1 over
Sigma1是1，另一个是下一个
Sigma 1 is a 1 and the other next guy is
a1，其余都是0，这是对的
a 1 and the rest are all 0 that's right
这是我能做到的最好的排名
it's the best I could do the rank was
只有两个，所以我无法到达任何地方
only two so I couldn't get anywhere so
这告诉你什么Sigmaplus是好的
that tells you what Sigma plus is okay
所以我描述了伪逆
so I described the pseudo-inverse then
用空间图片然后用
with a picture of spaces and then with a
矩阵的公式，现在我想
formula of matrices and now I want to
在最小的方格中使用它，所以现在我要去了
use it in least squares so now I'm going
说什么是最小二乘问题
to say what is the least squares problem
而解决它的第一种方法是
and the first way to solve it will be to
让我们做一个加号会给
let do to involve a plus will give the
解决方案好吧那是什么呢
solution okay so what is the what is the
最小二乘问题让我把它放在这里
least squares problem let me put it here
[掌声]
[Applause]
好吧，最小二乘问题很简单
okay the least squares problem is simply
你有一个方程ax等于B但a是
you have an equation ax equal B but a is
不可逆的，所以你解决不了的
not invertible so you can't solve it of
当然对于这啊，你可以找到你
course for which yeah you could find you
可以解决这个问题对于某些B的，如果B是
could solve it for certain B's if B is
在a的列空间中只是通过
in the column space of a then just by
列空间的含义有一个
the meaning of column space this has a
解决列空间中的向量
solution the vectors in the column space
是你可以得到的那些人
are the guys that you can get but the
你在正交空间中的向量
vectors in the orthogonal space you
不能得到所有其他的向量
cannot get all the rest of the vectors
你不能这么想，就像这样
you cannot get so suppose this is like
所以但总是a是M乘n等级R和
so but always a is M by n rank R and
然后我们在M时得到一个逆
that that then we get a inverse when M
等于N等于R是可逆的
equals N equals R that's the invertible
caseok我们用什么做系统
case ok what do we do with a system of
我们无法解决它的方程式
equations when we can't solve it that's
这可能是主要的应用
this is probably the main application in
1806所以你以前见过这个问题
1806 so you've seen this problem before
如果ax等于B没有，我们该怎么办？
what do we do if ax equal B has no
解
solution
所以通常B将是一个向量
so typically B would be a vector of
我们正在追踪的测量结果
measurements like we're tracking a
卫星，我们得到一些测量
satellite and we get some measurements
但我们常常得到太多
but and often we get too many
测量，当然有一个
measurements and of course there's a
它们的噪音很小，噪音很小
little noise in them and a little noise
意味着我们无法解决方程式
means that we can't solve the equations
也许我们就是每个人的情况
that maybe we're the case everybody
知道这就是这个地方
knows is where a where this this
方程就像表达一个直
equation is like expressing a straight
线经过数据点所以
line going through the data point so the
这些广场的着名例子是
the famous example of these squares is
直线适合直线
fit a straight line a straight line to
B的2B1B2我们有他们
the B's 2 B 1 B 2 we've got em
测量我们有测量
measurements we've got em measurements
物理或的机制
the physics or the mechanics of the
问题是非常线性但是
problem is pretty well linear but of
当然有噪音和直
course there's noise and the straight
线只有两个自由度
line only has two degrees of freedom
但是我们只有两个
however so we're going to have only two
在我们的矩阵列将只有两个
columns in our matrix a will be only two
高很多行的列
columns with many rows highly
矩形所以适合直线让
rectangular so fit a straight line let
我打电话给CXPlusD说这是
me call that line CX Plus D say this is
X方向这是蜜蜂
the X direction this is the the bees
方向，我们有一大堆
direction and we've got a whole bunch of
数据点，他们不在一条线或
data points and they're not on a line or
他们是在一条线上什么我怎么会怎样
they are in a line what how would I how
假设那些人确实躺在线上
what suppose those did lie on the line
什么会告诉我关于斧头等于B
what would that tell me about ax equal B
我没有说过我需要的一切但是
I haven't said everything I need to but
也许洞察力就是我在这里所追求的
maybe the insight is what I'm after here
如果我，如果我的分数是正确的那么
if I if my points are right on a line so
有一条直线贯穿其中
there is a straight line through them
这里的未知数是如此之低B所以斧头
the unknowns here is so low B so ax the
这里有未知数
unknowns here are
C＆D和右手边都是我的
C&D and the right hand side is all my
测量好吧假设没有我的
measurements okay suppose without my
画一幅画
drawing a picture
假设这些点上线
suppose the these points are on the line
这里是不同的X's
here here's the different X's the
测量x这里是不同的
measurement x here's the different
测量，但如果他们在一条线上
measurements but if they're on a line
那告诉我什么是线性的
what does that tell me about my linear
系统ax等于B它有一个解决方案
system ax equal B it has a solution
在一条线上意味着一切都是
being on a line means everything's
完美有一个解决方案，但会
perfect there is a solution but will
肯定有一个解决方案
there usually be a solution certainly
如果我只有两个参数两个，那就不行了
not if I have only two parameters two
未知两列这里的等级是
unknowns two columns here the rank is
会是两个，在这里我想
going to be two and here I'm trying to
击中任何嘈杂的测量值
hit any noisy set of measurements so of
一般来说，图片看起来很像
course in general the picture will look
那样的，我会找的
like that and I'm gonna look for the
最好的C和D所以我称之为CXCCX
best C and D so I'll call it C X C CX
加上D是的，对不起那就是我的
Plus D yeah right sorry that's that's my
那么那些是我的等式哦哦
line so those are my equation so oh
对不起，我经常把它写成C加DX吧
sorry I often write it C plus D X do you
如果我把常数术语放在首位，请注意
mind if I put the constant term first in
在高度困难的等式中
the in the highly difficult equation
这里是一条直线所以让我告诉你
here for a straight line so let me tell
你是我，所以这些是重点
you what I'm so these are the the points
你有一个测量X1X2的地方
where you have a measurement X 1 X 2 up
到XM，这些都是实际的
to X M and these are the actual
测量B1直到BM让我们说和
measurements B 1 up to BM let's say and
那我的方程式是啊
then my equations are yeah
我只想在这里设置你的矩阵
I'm just want to set up your matrix here
我只是想设置矩阵，所以我
I just want to set up the matrix so I
希望C得到每一个乘以
want C to get multiplied by ones every
时间，我想要契约
time and I want deed
得到乘以这些X的X1X2X3
get multiplied by these X's X 1 X 2 X 3
XM测量位置有
X M the measurement places and there was
无论如何测量和我的部分
a measurements anyway and the part my
问题是这没有解决方案等等
problem is this has no solution and so
那么当没有解决方案时我该怎么办？
so what do I do when there's no solution
好吧，我会做他所做的高斯
well well I'll do what gauss did he was
一个优秀的数学家，所以我会跟着他
a good mathematician so i'll follow his
意见，我也不会做这一切学期
advice and I won't do it all semester as
你懂
you know
所以，高斯的建议是最小化我
so but Gauss's advice was minimize I'll
责怪高斯的距离
blame it on the Gauss the distance
在ax+B之间平方l2范数
between a x + B squared the l2 norm
平方，这只是一个X.
squared which was which is just a X
减去B转置轴减去B它是a
minus B transpose ax minus B it's a
二次方和最小化它给了我一个
quadratic and minimizing it gives me a
线性方程组的系统，以便在端
system of linear equations so in the end
他们将有一个解决方案，所以这是
they will have a solution so that's the
我们有一个这些方块的整点
whole point of these squares we have an
不可解决的问题不是没有解决方案我们
unsolvable problem not no solution we
遵循高斯的建议，以获得最好的
follow a Gauss's advice to get the best
我们可以而且确实会产生答案
we can and that does produce an answer
所以这是这是，如果我乘这是
so this is this is if I multiply this as
出作为X变调转置斧子那
out as X transpose a transpose ax that
来自平方术语然后我
comes from the square term and then I
可能这些实际意志
have probably these actually will
可能我会得到其中的两个然后
probably I'll get two of those and then
一个具有导数0的常数项
a constant term that has derivative 0 so
它没有进入所以这就是我的意思
it doesn't enter so this is what I'm
最小化这是损失函数和
minimizing this is the loss function and
它导致让我们跳到这样
it leads to let's just jump to the so
这里的关键是我的方程式
the to the key here what equation do I
得到我的时候
get when I
什么方程式由最好的解决
for what equation is solved by the best
X最好的X最好的行为解决了
X the best X the best act solves the
着名所以这是回归和
famous so this is regression and
统计线性回归
statistics linear regression
其中一个主要的计算和
one of the main computations and
统计数据当然不仅仅是为了
statistics not of course just for
直线适合任何系统斧头
straight line fits but for any system ax
等于B将导致这个最小值
equal B that will lead to this minimum
将导致一个方程组
will lead to a system of equations that
我打算放一个盒子，因为
I'm going to put a box around because
它是如此根本，你愿意吗？
it's so fundamental and are you willing
告诉我这个等式是肯定的
to tell me what that equation is yes
感谢转置，它会来
thanks a transpose a it's gonna come
从那里你看到它倍数最好的x
from there you see it times the best x
等于给出的转置B.
equals a transpose B that gives the
最低限度
minimum
让我放弃检查你看到的
let me forego checking that you you see
二次项有矩阵
that the quadratic term has the matrix
在它，所以它的衍生物可能是
in it so it's derivative is may be may
这可以在导数是将
be the derivative of this is to a
转置斧头然后两个取消
transpose ax and then the two cancels
这两个也可以写
that two and this could also be written
因为X转置了转置B所以它是X.
as X transpose a transpose B so it's X
转反对转B中的
transpose against a transpose B that's
线性所以当我拿出衍生物
linear so when I take the derivative
这个国家的速度非常快
it's that country that's pretty fast
1806会耐心地得出那个但是
1806 would patiently derive that but
在这里，我让我给你一张照片
here I let me give you the picture that
我喜欢几何学，所以我们拥有它们
goes with it the geometry so we have we
有问题我们没有解决方案
have the problem no solution we have
高斯
Gauss's
最佳答案最小化了规范
best answer minimize the to norm of the
错误我们有结论的矩阵
error we have the conclusion the matrix
我们进去了，现在我想画一个
that we get in and now I want to draw a
与之相关的图片好在这里
picture that goes with it okay so here
是我想要的照片
is a picture I want to I want to have
那张照片中的那个列空间
column space of a there in that picture
当然，列中的零向量
of course the zero vectors in the column
这是所有这一切的空间
space of a so this is this is all
可能的向量是正确的
possible vectors ax right
你永远不会忘记那个专栏
you're never forgetting that the column
太空是我现在所需要的所有X
space is all the a X's now I've got to
将B放在图片中，这样就可以了
put B in the picture so where does this
矢量B所以我试图解决ax等于
vector B so I'm trying to solve ax equal
B但是失败了，如果我画B的话怎么办？
B but failing so what if I draw B in
这张照片我怎么画B我在哪里
this picture how do I draw B where do I
把它
put it
我应该把它放在列空间没有
shall I put it in the column space no
整点是不是在
the whole point is it's not in the
列空间它不是一个斧头它出来了
column space it's not an ax it's out
某处有乙好，然后什么
there somewhere B okay and then what's
随之而来的几何形状
the geometry that goes with these
正方形和正规方程组
squares and the normal equations and
高斯建议尽量减少错误
Gauss's suggestion to minimize the error
究竟会在那里将斧头是最好的斧头
what will where will ax be the best ax
我能做到的
that I can do
那么高斯就是那么高斯
where will so so so Gauss is what Gauss
已经产生了另一个他
has produced is a an a the other he
找不到X他会尽力而为
can't find an X he'll do his best he can
我们称那个人为X帽子
and we're calling that guy X hat and
这是找到X帽子的代数
this is the algebra to find X hat and
现在这里的图片在哪里
now where's the picture here where is
这个矢量斧头帽是最好的ik
this vector ax hat which is the best ik
斧头我们可以得到它必须如此
ax we can get so it has to be
在列空间，因为它是一个时代
in the column space because it's a times
东西，哪里是它在列
something and where is it in the column
空间
space
它的投影是x的一半和
it's the projection that's a x half and
这是你不能做的错误
here's the error which you couldn't do
任何关于B减去XF的事情都是如此
anything about B minus a X F yeah so
这是所有的投射权
it's the projection right so that all
这证明了，所以我们是我们在
this is justifying the so we're we're in
这些方块的第二种方法
the second approach to these squares
求解正规方程求解
solves the normal equations solve the
正常的方程式是的，那将是
normal equations yeah that would be the
第二种方法是最小二乘和
second approach to least squares and
大多数例子，如果他们不是很大或
most examples if they're not very big or
你很难创建一个矩阵
very difficult you just creates a matrix
转置a并调用MATLAB和
a transpose a and you call MATLAB and
解决你创建的线性系统
solve that linear system you create the
矩阵你创建右手边
matrix you create the right hand side
你解决它，这是普通的
and you solve it so that's the ordinary
运行中的磨
run-of-the-mill
这些方块问题就是这么做的
these squares problems just do it so
方法2只是这样做
that's method 2 just do it
我们的方法3是什么方法
what's method 3 for the same we're
在这里谈论同样的问题但是
talking about the same problem here but
现在我想它可能会多一点
now I'm thinking it may be a little more
困难这个矩阵a转置a
difficult this matrix a transpose a
可能几乎是单数高斯
might be nearly singular Gauss is
假设是啊是啊，当这样做
assuming that yeah yeah when did this
什么时候工作，它会工作
work when did this work and it will
继续在未来三年这个工作
continue to work in the next three this
如果假设有一个，这是好的
works this is good if assuming a has
独立专栏
independent columns
你更好地说清楚我声称
ya better just make clear I'm claiming
当a还没有那么是什么的时候
that when a hasn't so what's the what's
如果a具有独立性的推理
the reasoning if a has independent
列但可能没有足够的列
columns but maybe not enough columns
像这里一样，它只有两列
like here it's only got two columns
这显然无法做到
that's obviously not going to be able to
匹配任何右手边，但它有
match any right hand side but it's got
独立柱时，有
independent columns when a has
独立专栏然后我能说什么
independent columns then what can I say
关于这个矩阵，它是可逆的
about this matrix it's invertible
如果一个人有独立的话，高​​斯的计划就有效
Gauss's plan works if a has independent
然后这将是一个线性的列
columns then this would be a linear
代数步骤然后这将是
algebra step then this will be
你可以看到它的重要性
invertible you see the importance of
如果a具有独立列，则该步骤
that step if a has independent columns
这意味着它只有X空值
that means it has no null space only X
等于零处于零空间中的两个
equal zero is in the null space two
独立的列，但只有两个没有
independent columns but only two so not
足以解决系统但独立
enough to solve systems but independent
那么这个矩阵就可以了
then you're okay this matrix is
可逆的你可以做高斯所说的
invertible you can do what Gauss tells
你，但我们现在已经准备好了
you but we're prepared now we have to
想想，我真正想要的是什么
think okay so that what do I really want
要做我想要连接这个高斯的
to do I want to connect this Gauss's
因为伪逆的解决方案
solution to the pseudo inverse because
我声称他们都给了同样的东西
I'm claiming they both give the same
结果伪逆是的
result the pseudo inverse yeah the
伪逆将适用但我们有
pseudo inverse will apply but we have we
有喜欢的事，这是一个不
have like something this a is not
可逆的只是保持记忆
invertible just keep keep remembering
这个矩阵不可逆，但它是
this matrix it's not invertible but it's
它有独立的专栏我是什么
it has got independent columns what am i
他说，他们只是刚刚要回
saying they're just just going back to
图片
the picture
如果ahas是一个独立的矩阵
if if a has is a matrix with independent
列这个空间消失了
columns what space disappears in this
图片零空间消失了所以
picture the null space goes away so the
图片更简单，但它仍然是
picture is simpler but it's still the
这是一个转置的零空间
null space of a of a transpose this is
仍然很大，因为我只有两个
still pretty big because I only had two
列和一大堆行和
columns and a whole lot of rows and
这将在这里反映出来
that's gonna be reflected here
那么我想说的是什么呢
so what what am I trying to say I'm
想说这个答案是
trying to say that this answer is the
和伪逆回答一样吗？
same as the pseudo-inverse answer do we
甚至可能检查这一点
could possibly even check that point let
我先把它写下来
me write it down first
我声称答案加上B是
I claim that the answer a plus B is the
与来自这里的答案相同a
same as the answer coming from here a
当我转换一个倒转转换B.
transpose a inverse a transpose B when I
猜测等级空零是零
guess the null space is zero the rank is
无论你喜欢什么，我都说
all of em whatever you like to say I
相信那个方法就是这个
believe that that that method one this
用一个快速的公式来记住它
to it in one quick formula so remember
这是VSigmaplusutranspose
that this was V Sigma plus u transpose
这是一个转置是什么
right that's what a a transpose was that
这应该与此相信
this should agree with this I I believe
当零空间时，它们是相同的
those are the same when the null space
是不是在图片中这样的事实
isn't in the picture so the fact that
零空间仅仅是一个零向量
the null space is just a zero vector
意味着这反过来就是这样
means that this in this inverse does
存在所以这种逆存在但是aa
exist so this inverse exists but but a a
转置是不可逆的
transpose is not invertible
没有等不倒，因为aa
right no wait no inverse because a a
转置即将到来
transpose would be coming with a
转置所有这是一个空的空间
transpose all this is a null space of a
转置所以转置不是
transpose so a transpose is not
可逆的，但转换a是
invertible but but a transpose a is
你怎么会检查
invertible could you how would you check
你知道我什么时候才这样
that you see when i'm it's taken like
几乎整个小时获得
pretty much the whole hour to get a
的几何形状的图片
picture of the geometry of the
伪逆，所以这是伪
pseudo-inverse so this is the pseudo
逆，这就是那个矩阵
inverse and this is that matrix there
你知道它真的做到了最好
what you know it's really doing its best
事实上每个人都是反过来的
to be the inverse in fact everybody here
就像做他们最好是
is just like doing their best to be the
现在反过来这有多接近
inverse now how well is this how close
是我可以反过来
is that to being the inverse can I just
问你这个，然后我会做
ask you about that and then I'll make
这种联系然后我们就出局了
this connection and then we're out of
时间的接近程度，要作为
time how close is that to being the
反过来假设我乘以那个
inverse of a suppose I multiply that by
我能得到什么，所以只要注意我
a what do I get so so just notice if I
乘以我得到的东西
multiply that by a what do I get
我得到是的，我觉得我很棒，但不是
I get yeah I get I terrific but don't be
被骗以为这是
deceived to thinking that this is the
它的倒数只有它起作用了
inverse of a it only it worked on the
左侧，但它不会是好的
left side but it's not going to be good
在右边，所以如果我尝试，如果我
on the right-hand side so if I try if I
在这个方向乘以这个家伙
multiply a by this guy in that direction
我会像身份一样接近
I'll get like as close to the identity
因为我可以来，但我不会得到
as I can come but I won't get the
这样的身份所以这就是这个
identity that way so this is this a
小盒子说
little box to say
那么制作我是什么意思
so what's the point of making I'm
声称这是伪逆
claiming that this is the pseudo-inverse
无论这些空间是什么雨
whatever whatever these spaces the rain
可能很小只是这个有效
could be tiny just just one this works
当排名在我需要的时候
when the rank is in this I needed
独立的列，所以当排名是
independent columns so when the rank is
所以这是等级和那个
in so this is rank equal and that that
高斯工作，然后就可以得到一个接着一个
Gauss worked then I can get a one then
这是一个片面的反转，但它不是一个
it's a one-sided inverse but it's not a
双面逆我不能这样做，但我的
two-sided inverse I can't do that but my
那里的矩阵我可以找到片面的
matrix there I could find a one-sided
反过来获得2比2的身份，但我
inverse to get the 2 by 2 identity but I
永远不会
could never
乘以一些矩阵得到
multiply that by some matrix and get the
Nbyn认同那两个可怜的人
N by n identity those two pathetic
列没关系
columns okay
也许你觉得只是检查一下
maybe you feel like just checking this
只需要耐心，我的意思是什么
just takes patience what do I mean by
检查它我的意思是坚持伪
checking it I mean stick in the pseudo
SVD刚放入SVD和
the the SVD just put in the SVD and
像疯了一样取消，我想那就是
cancel like crazy and I think that'll
弹出你喜欢相信我因为它
pop out do you like believe me cuz it's
要认识你，会有点痛苦
gonna be a little painful 3 you know you
说我的V转置所有转置和
say my V transpose all transposed and
然后有东西，突然有
then something there and suddenly there
我有9个矩阵相乘但是
I've got 9 matrices multiplying away but
它会像各种各样的东西
it's gonna like how all sorts of things
将产生身份，最终
will produce the identity and in the end
这就是我所拥有的权利
that's what I'll have right right yep so
这就是这就是它
that's this is the this is the it's a
SVD的片面真逆
one-sided true inverse where the SVD
这个配方准备都没有
this formula is prepared to have neither
我们知道什么是可逆的
side invertible it's still we know what
Sigmaplus意味着无论如何都是如此
Sigma plus means anyway so under the
假设独立列高斯
assumption of independent columns Gauss
工作并给出与他们相同的答案
works and gives the same answer as their
伪逆
pseudo inverse
好吧三分钟
okay three minutes
这不是时间，但这是一个
that's hardly time but this being a
我觉得我应该用它哦天啊
mighty I feel I should use it oh my god
排名第三的是三号
number three so what's number three
关于第三是是是作为
about number three is is a is a as the
与第二个相同的要求相同
same requirement as number two the same
要求没有零空间，但它说
requirement of no null space but it says
如果我能先获得正交列
if I could get orthogonal columns first
那么这个问题就很容易了
then this problem would be easy so
大家都知道克施密特是一个
everybody knows that gram-schmidt is a
无聊的方式来自于
way boring way to get from from from
这两列得到两个正交
these two columns to get two orthogonal
列实际上是整个想法
columns actually the whole idea of
克施密特已经在那里了
gram-schmidt is already there for
因此我有两分钟
two-by-two so with so I have two minutes
我们可以做到让我们看看让我们做
and we can do it let's see let's do
克-施密特在这两列专栏上
gram-schmidt on these two columns column
列一列列，您会计我
column a column column you accountant I
不想使用U和V列y和z
don't want to use U and V column y&z
好吧，假设我想要正交化
okay suppose I want to orthogonalize
那些家伙是什么是克施密特的想法
those guys what's the gram-schmidt idea
我认为为什么这是非常好的不
i take why it's perfectly good no
y的问题是y向量
problem with y there's the y vector
他们都是那个人然后这个人不是
they're all ones then this guy is not
可能是正交的，它会消失
orthogonal probably to that it'll go off
还有一些在这个方向上有一个
and some this in this direction with an
这个角度不是九十度那么
angle that's not ninety degrees so what
我是否想要获得正交向量
do i do i want to get orthogonal vectors
我对第一个人没关系，但是
I'm okay with this first guy but the
第二个人与第一个人不正交
second guy isn't orthogonal to the first
所以我该怎么办
so what do I do
我如何在这张照片中如何来
how do I in this picture how do I come
使用与Y项目正交的向量
up with a vector orthogonal to Y project
我可以拿这个Z而且我拿它
I could I take this Z and I take its
投影所以Z有一点点
projection so Z has a little piece
Z矢量有一点点大块
that Z vector has a little big piece
已经朝Y的方向了
already in the direction of what Y which
我不想和一块正交的
I don't want and a piece orthogonal to
它这是我的另一片这是我的其他
it that's my other piece that's my other
因此，这就是为什么，这里是
piece so here's why and here's the the
这是Z减去负数a
this is that is Z minus the minus a
投影让我只是说不管是啊
projection let me just say whatever yeah
我不知道我是否画了这张照片
I don't know if I even drew that picture
右大概我没有什么反正
right probably I didn't anyway whatever
克-施密特的想法是公正的
the the gram-schmidt idea is just
以自然的方式正交化哦，我会
orthogonalize in the natural way oh I'll
回到那个开头
come back to that at the beginning of
下次再谈一谈
next time and say a word about the
第四种方式，但所以这个最小的方块
fourth way but but so this least squares
是不深入学习它是什么人
is is not deep learning it's what people
一个世纪以前，并继续做
did a century ago and continue to do for
很好的理由没关系，我会送出去的是
good reason okay and I'll send out that
关于班级和你的公告
announcement about the class and you
know the homework and you know the new
知道功课，你知道新的
截止日期是周五好，谢谢
due date is Friday good thank you